hey push students let's cover everything
you need for period
3 before we start print out the free
speed review sheet that goes along with
this video the link is in the
description below right now go through
period 3 Circle the people events and
vocab that you don't quite remember so
you know what you need to study then
once you're confident you know that
topic you can check it off and move to
the next one okay here we go period 3
starts with the French and Indian War
this was the American side of the Seven
Years War this is where the French and
their Native American Allies fought the
British and the American colonist over
the territory in the Ohio River Valley
this led to the Albany PL of Union by
Benjamin Franklin who also created the
Joiner die image to promote Colonial
Unity the British were victorious and
the war officially ended with the Treaty
of Paris France gave up all of its North
American land to the British whose
boundary now extended to the Mississippi
River the American colonists flooded
into the Ohio River Valley territory
upsetting the Native Americans living in
the region this led to pontiac's
rebellion and the British troops were
forced to help defend the colonists this
ended salutary neglect the British
troops maintained their presence in the
colonies King George III passed the
Proclamation of 1763 and Parliament
began taxing the colonies to help cover
the war debts the Sugar Act was the
first passed to help raise revenue from
the colonies this was followed by the
Stamp Act which was the first Direct Tax
colonists responded with the Stamp Act
Congress the formation of the Sons and
Daughters of Liberty who led the protest
and the boycotts and they claimed the
phrase no taxation without
representation Parliament was forced to
repeal the Stamp Act but passed the
decory ACT declaring absolute power over
the colonies next they passed the towns
and acts taxing tea glass paper and Lead
this also set up a system of tax
collectors and Customs agents to make
sure the taxes could be enforced the
presence of British troops and agents
increased tensions especially in port
cities like Boston leading to the Boston
Massacre Parliament also passed the Tea
Act forcing the colonists to only buy
British tea this led to the Boston Tea
Party The King responded with the
Intolerable Acts this included the
Boston Port act the Massachusetts
Government Act the administration of
justice Act Act and the Quartering Act
the other colonies feared that Britain
could do this to them as well leading to
the First Continental Congress all but
Georgia attended at this point colonists
were forced to pick a side you were
either a patriot or a loyalist the
American Revolution officially started
after shots were fired at Lexington and
conquered this forced all 13 colonies to
meet again in the second continental
congress there they made the Declaration
of Independence they established the
Continental Army and they wrote the
Articles of Confederation going into the
war England had one of the most powerful
armies and navies the large population
made the easy to recruit additional
troops and they were able to fund and
Supply the war but the Continental Army
knew the land were willing to engage in
Guerilla Warfare and had an ideological
commitment to Independence they also had
the leadership of George Washington
there are three key events you want to
know for the Revolutionary War first
Valley Forge where Washington's
leadership to help keep the Continental
Army together in the hardest winter
campaign next Saratoga where the
American victory cemented the alliance
with France and Yorktown where the
Continental Army and the French navy
forced the British to surrender the war
officially concluded with the Treaty of
Paris the British acknowledged the
American independence and they seeded
their North American territory east of
the Mississippi River now we can't talk
about the Revolution and not talk about
Enlightenment this was a period of
intellectual and cultural change in
Europe based on logic and reason this
played an instrumental role in colonists
starting to question authority this
directly inspired Thomas Payne's Common
Sense pet where he used logic and
reasion to prove that most of the
colony's problems were the fault of the
British why should a giant continent be
ruled by a tiny Island across the sea
his logic made complicated Enlightenment
ideas easy for common people to
understand and we declared independence
just a few months later Jefferson
included Enlightenment ideas in the
Declaration of Independence as well
especially consent of the governed in
natural rights now let's talk about the
Articles of Confederation after we
declared independence we needed a
government for our country so the
Continental Congress wrote the Articles
of Confederation they wanted a weak
government that couldn't rule with
tyranny it only included a legislative
branch that could declare war sign
treaties and request money however they
couldn't attacks or keep a standing army
they had no executive power to enforce
anything and couldn't settle disputes
between states there were a couple
successes under the Articles they were
able to sign the Treaty of Paris
officially ending the American
Revolution they also passed a 1785 land
ordinance and the Northwest Ordinance
the struggles to govern under the
Articles of Confederation reached their
Breaking Point with Shay's Rebellion
once the rebellion was finally put down
the colonies agreed that the Articles
needed revision the problem was that the
document was so flawed the founding
fathers had to abandon it altogether
they ended up creating a new form of
government and what became known as the
Constitutional Convention one of the
major issues debated at this meeting was
representation small states wanted the
New Jersey Plan while larger States
favored the Virginia Plan ultimately
they agreed to the Great Compromise this
formed a BAL legislature one house would
have representation based on population
and the other would be two per state the
other heated debate was over slavery
while some Representatives favored
abolition southern states were unwilling
to compromise on the institution so the
argument centered around whether the
enslaved would count towards
representation this led to the 3- fifths
compromise the Constitution set up the
three branches of government it set up
federalism where the power would be
shared between the federal government
and the state a system of checks and
balances was included so no one branch
could become too powerful once the
Constitution was finished it went to the
states for ratification factions
developed between the Federalists and
the Anti-Federalists the Federalist
wanted a stronger central government so
they wrote The Federalist Papers to
convince the states to ratify the
Constitution the Anti-Federalist opposed
the Constitution they felt it made the
federal government too strong they also
demanded a Bill of Rights be added
before they would ever consider
ratification after ratification the
Constitution went into effect in 1789
immediately following James Madison
wrote the first 10 amendments known as
the Bill of Rights although the Bill of
Rights was crafted to protect individual
liberties this did not extend to women
instead they were expected to stay home
and raise sons that would support the
Republic in 1789 George Washington was
elected the first president unanimously
he immediately set up his presidential
cabinet to help advise him on important
matters he selected Thomas Jefferson for
Secretary of State Alexander Hamilton
for Secretary of the Treasury and Henry
Knox a Secretary of War one of the
biggest foreign policy challenges
Washington faced was the French
Revolution despite the French being our
allies during the American Revolution
Washington ultimately issues a
proclamation of neutrality the biggest
domestic issue Washington handled was
the Whiskey Rebellion when Pennsylvania
Farmers protested the federal whiskey
tax Washington LED American troops to
put down the Rebellion this showed the
power of the executive branch and
represented a significant change from
the Articles of Confederation to the
Constitution after serving two terms
Washington stepped down in 1796 upon
leaving office he issued his farewell
address where he warned of the dangers
of political parties and to avoid
permanent alliances with foreign Nations
struggles moved during and after
Washington's presidency led to the
formation of political parties in our
first two-party system the Federalist
and Democratic Republican parties
debated economic policies Hamilton's
National Bank and how America should
respond to the French Revolution these
parties go head-to-head in the election
of 1796 John Adams won and he was our
only Federalist president the Adams
Administration was overshadowed by the
French Revolution in the quasa war when
Adam sent a delegation to France to try
and negotiate a peace the French tried
to extort the American diplomats at the
XYZ Affair when this news reached
America it sparked outrage and increased
tensions between the political parties
after facing heavy criticism Adams
passed the Alien and Sedition Acts this
made it illegal for the newspaper to
criticize the government ultimately
Adams handling of the French Revolution
led to his political downfall and he
lost the election of 1800 to Thomas
Jefferson now let's talk about what you
might see on exam day for causation be
ready to talk about the effects of the
French and Indian war or the causes of
the American Revolution for changing
continuity you may see a question about
changing American ideals over
Independence or a change in the
government from the Articles of
Confederation to the Constitution and
for comparison while you could see a
question asking about the Patriots and
the Loyalists you're more likely to see
a question asking about the the
difference in beliefs between the
Federalist and the Democratic Republican
parties check out the apish ultimate
review packet for more help like study
guides timelines and practice essays
follow the link in the description below
for a free preview if this video was
helpful like And subscribe thanks for
watching